<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Golang on Backendology</title>
    <link>https://jaredririe.github.io/categories/golang/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Golang on Backendology</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 13 Aug 2018 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://jaredririe.github.io/categories/golang/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>My Experience Using Hugo</title>
      <link>https://jaredririe.github.io/2018/08/13/experience-using-hugo/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 13 Aug 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jaredririe.github.io/2018/08/13/experience-using-hugo/</guid>
      <description>Disclaimer: this blog post is somewhat off topic in that it focuses on blogging more than backend software development. I think you will find this post informative if you have any interest in blogging, static site generation, or Go.
This post starts with a full example of using Hugo to create a simple blog. It then compares alternative blogging frameworks like Jekyll and Wordpress.
What is Hugo? Hugo is an open-source static site generator known for its performance and flexibility.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Lessons From Adopting Go at Qualtrics</title>
      <link>https://jaredririe.github.io/2018/08/06/lessons-from-adopting-go-qualtrics/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 06 Aug 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jaredririe.github.io/2018/08/06/lessons-from-adopting-go-qualtrics/</guid>
      <description>Back in September 2017, I teamed up with a coworker to give a presentation for the Utah Golang User Group. We chose to share the lessons we had learned as we adopted and scaled Go as one of the core programming languages at Qualtrics. Our intended audience was companies and developers who were interested in trying out Go and increasing its use within an organization. Many companies are considering Go because its popularity has only continued to rise (for good reason), so I&amp;rsquo;m excited to repost this content via my blog.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>