<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Distributed Systems on Backendology</title>
    <link>https://backendology.com/tags/distributed-systems/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Distributed Systems on Backendology</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 10 Sep 2018 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://backendology.com/tags/distributed-systems/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Designing a Comprehensive Course in Distributed Systems: Reading List</title>
      <link>https://backendology.com/2018/09/10/distributed-systems-course-reading-list/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 10 Sep 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://backendology.com/2018/09/10/distributed-systems-course-reading-list/</guid>
      <description>In a recent conversation at work, I learned about MIT&amp;rsquo;s distributed systems course. As the majority of the content is available online through the course website, I was just about ready to dive in, follow the course, and report on what I learned. But then I had this thought: I am not formally a student anymore, so I should take more ownership of my learning. I should design my own comprehensive course in distributed systems!</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Multiple Layers of Caching</title>
      <link>https://backendology.com/2018/08/27/multiple-layers-caching/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 27 Aug 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://backendology.com/2018/08/27/multiple-layers-caching/</guid>
      <description>Caching is one of my favorite topics in technology. I&amp;rsquo;ve been fortunate enough to approach this problem from both a hardware and software perspective. This blog post will cover some of the basics of caching, yet focus on the importance of having multiple layers of caching in a system. I think this is a key point worth emphasizing as I&amp;rsquo;ve seen it commonly misunderstood.
A caching anecdote One of the systems I built at Qualtrics could be described as the &amp;ldquo;back of the backend&amp;rdquo; as it was a critical storage system that many services relied on, yet had no service dependencies itself.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Microservices: Are We Making a Huge Mistake?</title>
      <link>https://backendology.com/2018/08/21/microservices-huge-mistake/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 21 Aug 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://backendology.com/2018/08/21/microservices-huge-mistake/</guid>
      <description>There is a clear trend in the software industry moving away from large, monolithic systems to fine-grained services known as &amp;ldquo;microservices.&amp;rdquo; While compelling, microservices introduce their own set of challenges and fallacies. This post considers the benefits and drawbacks of a microservices architecture (MSA) and contemplates the question: are we making a huge mistake in adopting this kind of architecture?
Relationship to &amp;ldquo;distributed systems&amp;rdquo; First, let&amp;rsquo;s clear up some terminology that you may find confusing.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>What This Blog is All About</title>
      <link>https://backendology.com/2018/07/14/what-this-blog-is-all-about/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 14 Jul 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://backendology.com/2018/07/14/what-this-blog-is-all-about/</guid>
      <description>&amp;ldquo;Backendology&amp;rdquo;?  There are only two hard things in Computer Science: cache invalidation and naming things (Phil Karlton).
 Or, my favorite variant:
 There are only two hard things in Computer Science: cache invalidation, naming things, and off by one errors (Unknown)
 Naming is hard. Backendology isn&amp;rsquo;t a real word. Like the programmer who decides to write a lengthy comment rather than coming up with a better name, I&amp;rsquo;ll try to explain what I intended when I named this blog Backendology.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>